<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Carpentries Offline</title>
<link>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/</link>
<atom:link href="https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Projects we are currently working on
</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:14:34 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Bootable Flash Drive</title>
  <link>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/FlashDrive.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Important
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Watch this space for the latest flashdrive image. When it is ready, this will become a link to the download.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>It is possible to run a complete operating system just from a flashdrive. As an alternative to using a Raspberry Pi computer to act as a server, you can write the CarpentriesOffline OS to a flashdrive and then boot your computer from the flashdrive. The CarpentriesOffline Os is built on Slax which, in turn, is built on Debian. <a href="../documentation/flashdrive_step_by_step.html">Step-by-step instructions for creating a CarpentriesOffline flashdrive</a>.</p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>flashdrive</category>
  <guid>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/FlashDrive.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:14:34 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/images/flashdrive.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="203" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The miniHPC</title>
  <link>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/miniHPC.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Pixie is our prototype High Performance Computer (HPC), built with:</p>
<ul>
<li>6 x Raspberry Pi (RPi) 4GB single board computers (SBC).</li>
<li>An SSD drive with a power USB adapter</li>
<li>An 8 port PXE TP-Link switch</li>
<li>A dual USB fan</li>
<li>Loads of 10BaseT Cat6 ethernet cables</li>
<li>3D printed DIN Rail stand</li>
<li>3D printed RPi cases</li>
</ul>
<section id="why-pi" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-pi">Why Pi?</h2>
<p>This projected started shortly after the Covid lockdown and because RPis are nowhere to be found, the decision was made to buy Rock 4SE SBCs. The problems is that these boards are only available at two companies in the UK, RS and OKdo, and OKdo is a subsidiary of RS. We noticed that they have discounts available for education so we started an enquiry into the possibility of getting these discounts. Unfortunately this is where the wheels came off. It took three weeks before we could eventually place an order and when the last batch of items, the PoE hats, arrived, they didn’t fit the Rock 4 boards. While this was going on, to not waste time, we started putting together a mini-HPC using Raspberry Pis that we already own.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-a-mini-hpc" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-a-mini-hpc">Why a mini HPC?</h2>
<p>Many people have built Raspberry Pi HPCs, why do we want to include this as part of the CarpentriesOffline project? The need for this project became apparent in February 2023 when we ran a workshop for the N8 at Newcastle University using the Carpentries Incubator lesson, Introduction to High-Performance Computing. There are a few things that seem to, almost always, go wrong when running a workshop such as this one:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>People do not register for HPC accounts before the workshop. Most HPCs will have certain hoops you need to jump through when you want to obtain a user account on them. There are often time delays to get the accounts approved which means that if the learners did not obtain their logins before the workshop they are not guaranteed to get a login arranged on the day of the workshop.</li>
<li>Login nodes can experience problems due to users running processes on them that they are not supposed to. When this happens others users cannot log in. Obviously, workshop have to happen within a certain time frame and if the learners can’t get logged in, the workshop can’t continue.</li>
<li>The length of queues and the load on an HPC cannot be controlled and if it so happens that many other users are accessing the HPC on the day of the workshop, access can be slow and jobs in the queue might not get completed in a timely manner for the workshop.</li>
<li>Last but not the least are problems with The Internet itself.</li>
</ol>
<p>HPCs are not easy to set up. Many document their processes but it still requires quite a lot of expertise to set up. What we would like to do is to create images of the SD cards required to boot the RPis and/or Rock Pis straight into an HPC. Instructors should be able to obtain specified hardware and know how to connect everything, write the OS image to an SD card or SSD and boot the computer into a usable HPC state.</p>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>minihpc</category>
  <guid>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/miniHPC.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:14:34 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/images/pixie.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The OfflineDataSci Python package</title>
  <link>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/offlinedatasci.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>offlinedatsci is a tool for supporting teaching and doing data science in internet-limited environments. It helps you download and configure common tools for teaching and doing data science without an internet connection including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Installers for data science languages: Currently R and Python</li>
<li>Installers for common data science IDEs: Currently RStudio</li>
<li>Partial, data science focused, local mirrors of package repositories: Currently CRAN (for R) and PyPI (for Python)</li>
<li>Locally browseable clones of data science teaching websites: Currently Data Carpentry, Software Carpentry, and Library Carpentry</li>
</ul>
<p>The package is also used to create the CarpentriesOffline operating system image for the Raspberry Pi and FlashDrive projects which allow you to turn a Raspberry Pi computer or your laptop (with the use of the FlashDrive) into a web server and an access point for learners to connect to. It can be used to quickly update all materials to the newest versions when an internet connection is available.</p>
<p><a href="https://offlinedatasci.readthedocs.io/">Package Documentation</a></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>offlinedatasci</category>
  <guid>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/offlinedatasci.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:14:34 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/images/pypilogo.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>CarpentriesOffline with a Raspberry Pi</title>
  <link>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/RaspberryPi.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>For the last year we have been working on creating an image that can be written to an SD card which is then used to boot a Raspberry Pi (RPi). The SD card turns the RPi into:</p>
<ul>
<li>an access point for learners to connect to with their computers,</li>
<li>a web server with all the learning materials</li>
<li>a Gitea server which acts as a replacement for GitHub to practise the collaborative parts of version control with Git</li>
</ul>
<p>We have, so far, experienced a few challenges with this solution.</p>
<ul>
<li>there seems to be a limit to the number of computers that can connect to the RPi access point</li>
<li>RPis suddenly became impossible to obtain after Covid lockdown - however, they are available again.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="../documentation/rpiimage_step_by_step.html">Step-by-step instructions for creating the SD card image</a></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>sdcard</category>
  <guid>https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/RaspberryPi.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 08:14:34 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://carpentriesoffline.org/projects/images/sd_card.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="164" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
